<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>  <!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="info"
  docName="draft-daley-rswg-postal-addresses-00"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates="7991"
  submissionType="editorial"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <front>
    <title>Deprecating the use of processed addresses within the &lt;postal&gt; element in RFCXML</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-daley-rswg-postal-addresses-00"/>
   
    <author fullname="Jay Daley" initials="J" surname="Daley">
      <organization>IETF Administration LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1000 N. West St, Ste 1200</street>
          <city>Wilmington</city>
          <region>DE</region>
          <code>19801</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>        
        <email>jay@staff.ietf.org</email>  
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <area>RFC Editor</area>
    <workgroup>RFC Series Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>postal address</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a change to the RFXCXML syntax to deprecate the use of processed addresses within the &lt;postal&gt; element and to recommend the use of the unprocessed addresses as this is simpler to use, does not rely on a third-party library, and leaves address formatting decisions to authors.'Deprecate' is used in the standard way it is used in software engineering - processed addresses can still be used, but their use is not recommended and a warning emitted when they are used that they will later be removed from RFCXML.</t>
    </abstract>
    <note removeInRFC="true">
      <name>About This Document</name>
      <t>Status information for this document may be found at <eref
        target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-daley-rswg-postalline/"/>. </t>
      <t> Discussion of this document takes place on the RFC Series Working Group Editorial Stream
        Working Group mailing list (<eref target="mailto:rswg@rfc-editor.org"/>), which is archived
        at <eref target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/browse/rswg/"/>. </t>
      <t>Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at <eref
        target="https://github.com/JayDaley/draft-daley-rswg-postalline"/>.</t>
    </note>
 
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC7991"/> defines the RFCXML language (at the time called the "xml2rfc vocabulary") as an authoring and publication format for Internet-Drafts and RFCs. For postal addresses, <xref section="2.37" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7991"></xref> defines the &lt;postal&gt; element and allows addresses to be written in one of two ways:</t>
      <ol>
        <li>Using the &lt;city&gt;, &lt;code&gt;, &lt;region&gt; &lt;street&gt;and &lt;country&gt; elements.  These can be provided in any order and are then processed using a third-party library during the rendering process to check the validity of the address and to determine the ordering and formatting of the output, based on the local standards for that country/region as encoded in the library.  Addresses specified in this way are referred to here as 'processed' addresses.</li>
        <li>Using a sequence of &lt;postalline&gt; elements. These are used in the order provided, without any checking, as the text for the rendered formats. Addresses specified in this way are referred to here as 'unprocessed' addresses</li>
      </ol>
      <t>Processed addresses were introduced with the intent of providing better semantic information about addresses that could have future uses. In order to achieve that, the above set of generic elements were specified with the intent that could be used to encode any postal address. However, experience with the used of processed addresses, has shown that they come with significant problems that outweigh any potential benefits:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>Authors complain that the formatting of addresses produced by the library does not correspond to how they would format them.</li>
        <li>Following complaints from authors that the elements do not semantically correspond to their local addresses, RFCXML was extended after the publication of <xref target="RFC7991"/> to include the &lt;cityarea&gt;, &lt;extaddr&gt;, &lt;pobox&gt; and &lt;sortingcode&gt; elements, as documented in <xref target="I-D.levkowetz-xml2rfc-v3-implementation-notes"/>, which has just complicated matters further.</li>
        <li>The address rules encoded into the third-party are incomplete and in some cases out of date.</li>
        <li>The third-party library is no longer maintained and no alternative has been identified.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>Further, experience has shown that there is a value in a semantic tag for the country of an address, but the &lt;country&gt; element is only allowed within processed addresses and not within unprocessed addresses and so any unprocessed addresses are more complex to parse for country information.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <name>Proposed changes</name>
      <t>In order to address the problems identified above, a number of changes are proposed to RFCXML along with guidance for the RFC Production Center (RPC) on the use of addresses in RFCs. These changes intentionally result in a new RFCXML grammar that is backwards compatible - i.e. that all existing documents written in RFCXML v3 will continue to validate with the new grammar. This proposal also intentionally does not require any change to be made published RFCs.</t>
        <section>
          <name>Changes to RFCXML</name>
          <t>This document updates the RFCXML grammar in <xref target="RFC7991"/> as follows:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>The use of the &lt;city&gt;, &lt;code&gt;, &lt;region&gt; &lt;street&gt;, &lt;cityarea&gt;, &lt;extaddr&gt;, &lt;pobox&gt; and &lt;sortingcode&gt; within &lt;postal&gt; as specified in <xref section="2.37" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7991"/> and further extended by the addition of new elements, is deprecated. They may still be used but the the xml2rfc tool will emit a warning that their use is deprecated.</li>
            <li>The &lt;country&gt; element can now be used optionally (zero or one times) within the &lt;postal&gt; element when &lt;postalline&gt; elements are used, as specified in <xref section="2.37" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7991"/>.</li>
          </ol>
          <t>This is implemented in the grammar with this line changing from:</t>
          <sourcecode type="rnc">
            <![CDATA[
| postalLine+)
            ]]>
          </sourcecode>
          <t>to:</t>
          <sourcecode type="rnc">
            <![CDATA[
| (postalLine+, country?))
            ]]>
          </sourcecode>
        </section> 
      <section>
        <name>Rendering of unprocessed addresses</name>
        <t>The rendering of unprocessed addresses as specified in <xref section="2.38" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7991"/> is adapted so that, if the &lt;country&gt; element is specified alongside &lt;postalline&gt; elements, then each element is rendered in the order provided, each on a new line, thereby affording authors full control of how the address appears.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Possible future removal of the deprecated elements</name>
        <t>Deprecation allows for the deprecated elements to be removed in a future revision to RFCXML without further warning. Any such removal should take care to allow authors to continue to specify just the country and no other part of the address.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Grammar versions and compatibility</name>
        <t>These changes are backwards compatible for older documents. That means that any RFCXML document that validates with the RFCXML grammar before this change, will continue to validate. The deprecation warning may lead to some choosing to update their documents, but that is not required.</t>
        <t>These changes are not backwards compatible for older versions of the grammar. That means that documents written after this grammar is introduced that include the &lt;country&gt; element alongside &lt;postalline&gt; elements, will not validate against older versions of the grammar.</t>
        <t>Since the publication of <xref target="RFC7991"/> there have been multiple versions of the RFCXML grammar published that have the same compatibility attributes, such as the recent change to add the 'editorial' stream. See <xref target="v3rnc"/> for details. None of these have been assigned a different version number (what may appear to be version numbering of the grammar is in fact a reference to the version of xml2rfc that first included this changed grammar) and so this document also does not assign the new grammar a different version number.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Impact on existing documents</name>
        <t>Nothing in this document changes the current principle of immutability of RFCs. RFCXML RFCs do not need to have any postal addresses with processed addresses rewritten as unprocessed addresses as there is no benefit in doing so. It is recognised that this will likely mean that a point is reached where the version of xm2rfc current at that time cannot reliably render processed addresses in previously published RFCs in precisely the same way as they were at the time of publication.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <name>Use of processed addresses in RFCs from this point forwards</name>
      <t>A point will need to be reached where processed addresses no longer appear in RFCs. The timing of this is best determined by the RPC in consultation with the stream managers, so it is left to the RPC to decide when they cease to accept processed addresses.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document should not affect the security of the Internet.</t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7991.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="I-D.levkowetz-xml2rfc-v3-implementation-notes" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-levkowetz-xml2rfc-v3-implementation-notes-13">
          <front>
            <title>Implementation notes for RFC7991,</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Levkowetz" fullname="Henrik Levkowetz">
              <organization>Elf Tools AB</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="September" day="16" year="2021"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>
                This memo documents issues and observations found while implementing RFC 7991. Individual notes are organised into separate sections, depending on their character.
              </t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-levkowetz-xml2rfc-v3-implementation-notes-13"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="v3rnc" target="https://github.com/rfc-format/v3grammar">
          <front>
            <title>GitHub repository for version of the v3 RFCXML grammar</title>
            <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
      
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
      </references>
    </references>
    
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This document </t>
    </section>
             
 </back>
</rfc>
